Finding aid to the Elizabeth A. Nichols papers CA.MS.00312
Smith College Archives
Elizabeth A. Nichols papers
1989-1990
Smith College Archives
Nichols, Elizabeth A.
CA.MS.00312
0.417 linear feet (1 container)
Elizabeth A. Nichols is a 1990 Smith alumna. This collection contains notes, articles, and correspondence she collected in the course of researching her senior thesis in history: "Paradise Lost and Regained: Experiences of Refugee Professors at Smith College."
Biographical / Historical
Elizabeth A. Nichols was a member of the Class of 1990 and graduated cum laude. She resided in Oak House.
Scope and Contents
For her senior thesis "Paradise Lost and Regained: Experiences of Refugee Professors at Smith College" Elizabeth A. Nichols attempted to investigate the academic and personal experiences of seventeen European academics who taught at Smith College in the 1930s and 1940s. Her thesis was awarded high honors. Most of these individuals had fled Germany and other parts of Europe in order to escape oppression by the German National Socialist regime. The research materials in this collection include information culled from the Smith College Archives and other sources on several of the professors. It also includes Nichols's detailed notes on the papers of the Emergency Committee in Aid of Displaced Foreign Scholars located in the Manuscripts and Archives Division of the New York Public Library. The heart of the collection consists of responses to a query letter sent by Nichols to more than fifty Smith alumnae whom she hoped would have recollections of the professors in question. She appears to have chosen her correspondents based (at least in part) on their membership in the German Club or residence in the German House while at Smith College. Those alumnae who were able to reply substantively provided thoughtful reflections about the personalities and teaching styles of (some of the) teachers in question. Certain letters also describe in some detail the tensions between Nazi sympathizers and opponents that developed at the German House, and on campus, in the 1930s.
A list of the professors in Nichols's query is below. The weight of alumnae recollections centers on three of these: the historian Hans Kohn (1891-1971), who taught at Smith from 1933 to 1949 and was immensely popular with students; German literature professor Martin Sommerfeld (1894-1939), who taught at Smith from 1936 to 1939; and Matthias Schmitz (1899-?), who was not a refugee at all but (apparently) a member of the Nazi Party. The flamboyant Schmitz taught at Smith from 1934-1939 and students had wildly differing opinions of him. This collection contains both published and unpublished material regarding Schmitz.
Anita Ascher German
Herbert Busemann Math
Alfred Einstein Music
Susanne Engelmann German
Mannfred Kridl Slavic Studies
Hans Kohn History
Lilly Lorentz Physics
George Michaelides Religion
Renato Poggioli Italian
George Poyla Math
Annelies Rose Psychology
Maja Schade Physical Education
Matthias Schmitz German
Oskar Seidlin German
Martin Sommerfeld German
Jean Wahl French
Edgard Wind Art History
The collection also contains published articles on the refugee scholar experience in the U.S. and one set of notes from an oral interview. There was presumably more evidence from oral interviews that did not survive.
The collection contains a copy of Nichols's query letter and two faculty evaluations of the thesis by Dan Horowitz and Hans Vaget, but does not contain the thesis itself. At this writing, the Smith College Library also did not possess a copy of the thesis.
Related Material
- RG 22. Buildings and Grounds, German House (8 Bedford Terrace)
- RG 42. Faculty
- RG 52. German Club
- RG 80. Class of 1990
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Elizabeth A. Nichols Papers were donated to the Smith College Archives by Ms. Nichols in February 2007.
- General (Box 2300.2, Folder 1)
- Index card file (Box 2300.2, Folder 2)
- Smith Faculty-Asher, Anita (Box 2300.2, Folder 3)
- Smith Faculty-Engelmann, Susanne (Box 2300.2, Folder 4)
- Smith Faculty-Kohn, Hans (Box 2300.2, Folder 5)
- Smith Faculty-Kridl, Manfried (Box 2300.2, Folder 6)
- Smith Faculty-Schmitz, Matthias (Box 2300.2, Folder 7)
- Smith Faculty-Seidlin, Oskar (Box 2300.2, Folder 8)
- Smith Faculty-Sommerfeld, Martin (Box 2300.2, Folder 9)
- Smith Faculty-Wahl, Jean (Box 2300.2, Folder 10)
- Smith Faculty-Wind, Edgard (Box 2300.2, Folder 11)
- Refugee Scholars (Box 2300.2, Folder 12)
- Recollection, Nelly Schargo Hoyt '43 (Box 2300.2, Folder 13)
- Interview-Ruth Mahoney Peck, 1989 (Box 2300.2, Folder 14)
- Research Notes-Emergency Committee in Aid of Displaced Foreign Scholars (NYPL) (Box 2300.2, Folder 15)
- FBI FOIA Inquiry, 1989-90 (Box 2300.2, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, October 1-31, 1989 (Box 2300.2, Folder 17)
- Correspondence, November 1-29, 1989 (Box 2300.2, Folder 18)
- Correspondence, December 1, 1989-August 27, 1990 (Box 2300.2, Folder 19)
- Evaluations of thesis, 1990 (Box 2300.2, Folder 20)